Support for NPR Music comes from Capital
One, proud supporters of NPR Music and
the Tiny Desk Contest. What's in your
wallet? Learn more at capitalone.com.
>> [music]
>> Well,
>> [singing and music]
>> on this train
I am
a soul
>> [singing]
[music]
>> went down that Georgia
>> [singing]
>> line.
The [music] engine [singing]
passed
at 6:00
and the cab
>> [singing]
>> passed by
>> [music]
>> night.
In the pines, [singing]
in the pines,
where the sun [music]
never shines, and we [singing] shiver
when the cold [music]
wind blows.
When
I asked
my captain
for the time
of day, [music and singing]
he said he threw
his watch
away.
>> [music]
>> Well,
>> [singing]
>> long steel
rail
and a short
cross tie,
I'm
>> [music]
>> on my way
>> [singing]
>> back home.
Well, in the pines,
in the pines,
where [singing] the sun
sun shines,
and we shiver
when the cold, [music and singing] cold
wind blows.
>> [singing]
[singing]
[music]
>> Little girl, little girl,
what have
I done
to make you treat me so?
You caused
me to weep [music]
and caused me to moan,
and you caused [music and singing]
me to lose my home.
>> [music]
>> Look up,
look down
>> [singing]
>> that lonesome
[music] road.
Hang down
>> [singing]
>> your little head and cry.
Cry.
Say if you
>> [singing and music]
>> love me
as I
love you,
won't you go
with [singing and music] me
or die?
In the pines, [music]
in the pines, where the sun never
shines,
>> [singing]
>> and we shiver
when the cold, [music]
cold wind blows.
>> [singing]
[singing]
[music]
[cheering]
[applause]
>> Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you SO MUCH.
>> [cheering]
>> ALL RIGHT.
WE LOVE THAT.
THANK YOU. THIS has been such an
exciting project to work on with Béla
Fleck, and we started on this a long
time ago.
Um but the thing that I love One of the
things I love about it is a lot of this
music is as old as the music that I have
sung my whole career. It's so many Civil
War songs, so much that came over from
the UK, from even earlier, and so many
references were constantly shared,
whether it was 10,000 years or Lonesome
Pines or any number of images have gone
across the country. And in fact, I asked
the Smithsonian at one point, "What's
the definitive version of one of these
songs?" And he said, "You know, it
really depended on which hill you lived
on."
So, it's ancient.
Um so, this next piece is another
gorgeous folk melody that is also from
the US. I believe it was from
North Carolina, I think. And this was
another Civil War song, He's Gone Away.
Absolutely beautiful.
He's gone [singing]
away
for to stay
a little while. [singing]
But, he's coming back
if he goes
10,000 [singing]
miles.
Oh, who
>> [singing]
>> will tie
my shoe?
And who
will glove
my hand?
>> [singing]
>> And who will kiss
my ruby lips
when he
is gone? [singing]
Look away.
>> [singing]
>> Over
the rainbow.
>> [singing]
>> I'm going [singing]
away
to leave
you, love.
I'm going
>> [singing and music]
>> away for a while.
But I'll return
to you [music]
someday [singing]
if
I go 10,000
miles.
The storms
>> [music and singing]
>> on the ocean,
the heavens may cease [music]
[singing] to be,
this world
>> [singing]
>> will lose
its [music] motion,
love,
if
>> [singing]
>> I grow false [music] to thee.
Have
you seen those [singing] lonesome
doves [music]
flying [singing] from pine to pine?
They're
mourning for their own
>> [singing]
>> true [music] love,
just like
I mourn for [singing and music] mine.
The storms
>> [singing]
>> on the ocean,
>> the heavens
may cease to be,
this [music and singing] world
will
lose its motion,
love,
if
I prove false [singing]
to thee.
>> [music]
>> sun,
>> [singing]
>> the
ocean.
The heavens may cease [singing] to be.
This world
>> [singing]
>> will lose [music]
its motion
love
if I prove false
to thee.
>> [music]
[music]
>> He's gone
[singing] away
I thought
to stay
a little while.
But he's coming back [singing]
if he goes 10,000
miles. [singing]
And it's papa
>> [singing]
>> will tie
my shoe.
And mama will [singing] glove
my hand.
And you [singing] will kiss
my
ruby
lips when breathe.
return. [singing]
Look away.
>> [singing]
>> Look away.
>> [music]
>> Over yonder
>> [singing]
>> road.
>> [music]
[applause]
>> Thank you. Thank you.
Yes. Yes.
>> Hi.
Um these incredible musicians we're
fortunate enough to have with us. That's
Mark Schatz on the bass.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> Jake Stargel on the guitar.
>> [applause]
>> Michael Cleveland on THE FIDDLE.
>> [applause and cheering]
[applause]
>> SIERRA HULL ON THE MANDOLIN AND VOCALS.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> AND I'M RENEE FLEMING.
>> SEE, THE AMAZING thing is that Béla
is loved by so many musicians across
multiple genre. You are, you are. So,
when we started talking about this
project, he was able We were just
brainstorming and dreaming, and he was
able to really enlist the help of all of
the best players. And to be able to
perform with you all has just been such
an incredible dream. You're amazing
musicians. I don't know how you get that
sound out of this instrument, too. I've
heard this instrument a lot in my life.
It's a big sound, Michael.
>> It's big and loud.
>> [laughter]
>> Big and loud. So, we always want to be
>> ever, but it's big and loud.
>> [laughter]
>> Oh, you're in tune. So, let's talk a
little bit about um the the ideas behind
the themes of the project.
>> Well, we started out um just picking
songs we liked. And we came up with a
little pile of songs we liked, which was
good cuz that's what we were getting
together to do.
And um and then after a while we came
back to them uh and thought about like
what goes with these songs? What what is
here? And we discovered to our surprise
that there was there was kind of a a
story line in the songs that we recorded
uh unconsciously chosen. And so when we
finished the the record and and found
other songs to record, we found songs
that continued that story line and
fitted in. It's a lot of love and loss,
uh war yeah.
>> I mean, it's the title is a Joni
Mitchell song and we were surprised to
discover that we were both Joni Mitchell
fans when we were younger and well,
still are.
>> We're still younger.
>> Yeah, who's not? Exactly, who's
[laughter] not? Yes,
still are. So, um that's why it's called
the fiddle and the drum. But, thank you
for supporting us and being here. It's
really exciting. We have one more song
um called the blackest crow and do we
have anything to say about that? It's a
really interesting text.
>> The crow is very, very dark.
>> Yeah.
>> That's about all we know.
No, I don't know Is there something you
found?
>> Um
Well, it's just another one that dates
back and I think this is an American
song, so uh
we don't know it that much about the
history of it this moment.
So, here we go.
>> The time has come, [singing]
my dearest
dear,
for you and I
>> [singing]
>> and I to
part?
How little [singing] do we know
of the grief
and the woe
in my poor
>> [singing]
>> aching heart?
It's what
>> [singing]
>> I suffer
for my
sake.
Believe
me, dear,
it's true.
I wish that you could [singing] stay
with me,
or I could [singing] go
with you.
>> [music]
>> I wish [music and singing] my breast
were made of glass, wherein you
[singing] might [music] behold.
Your name in secret I
>> [singing]
>> would write in letters made of gold.
[music and singing]
Your name in secret
I would write. Believe me when [singing]
I say,
>> [music]
>> you are the man that I
>> [singing]
>> love best until my dying day.
>> [music]
[music]
>> When you
>> [singing]
>> are
>> [music]
>> on some distant shore, think on your
absent
friend. [singing and music]
And when the
wind blows
>> [music]
[singing]
>> high and
clear,
of
thee [singing]
>> [music]
>> I'll praise send.
And when the
wind blows
high and
>> [music]
>> clear,
praise send
is love
to me
>> [singing]
>> that I may know
by your
hand
right? How
times have gone
>> [music and singing]
>> with
thee.
The blackest crow that [singing] ever
flew [music]
would truly
turn to white.
>> [music]
>> If ever
I prove false to you, bright day would
turn
>> [singing and music]
>> to night.
Bright day would turn to [music] night,
my dear. The
elements would
mourn. If
ever I prove false to you,
the seas would rage
>> [music]
>> and burn.
If ever
>> [singing]
>> I prove false to you, the seas would
rage
>> [singing]
>> and burn.
>> [music]
>> Yeah.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> THANK YOU.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> THANK YOU. YOU'RE ALL RIGHT.
>> [applause]
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU.
>> [applause]
[cheering]
>> THANKS FOR WATCHING. SUPPORT FOR NPR
Music comes from Rivian, makers of
all-electric adventure vehicles,
including the R1S three-row SUV. More at
rivian.com.
A quick update before you go. We're
doing another Tiny Desk giveaway. Enter
by September 12th, [music] 2026, and you
and a friend could win a free trip to DC
to see a Tiny Desk concert live [music]
in person. You even get to choose which
upcoming show you want to see, and it's
completely free to enter. Just go to
npr.org/tinydeskgiveaway.
Entering is completely free, but you can
get more entries by snagging some
limited edition Tiny Desk merch or by
making a special donation to the NPR
network. Learn more and enter today at
npr.org/tinydeskgiveaway.
[music]